Guide to the Department of History Records, 1932-[ongoing] UA.25.23.0001
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Department of History records
1932-[ongoing]
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University. Department of History
UA.25.23.0001
31.05 Linear Feet
Collection contains records pertaining to the operation and activities of the Department of History and its faculty at Duke University, 1932-[ongoing]. Materials present include administrative files from the Office of the Chair, Director of Graduate Studies, and Director of Undergraduate Studies: correspondence, memoranda, departmental meeting minutes, budget and course material, committee files, and various subject files. The records also include course papers, inactive faculty files, Nixon Library material, and external review files. University Archives staff must be consulted in order to determine the extent of access restrictions.
about 37, 250 Items
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the office of origin and the University Archivist is required for use. After twenty-five years, records that have been processed may be consulted with the permission of the University Archivist.
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
Portions of these materials are restricted by donor request.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Department of History Records were received by the University Archives as a transfer between 1961 and 2002.
Historical Note
The study of history emerged as a separate field of study at Trinity College in the late nineteenth-century supported by a change in popular attitudes, interests, and the ongoing professionalization of the field of historical inquiry. In 1891, Trinity College became the first southern educational institution to establish a distinct chair of history. In 1896, Stephen B. Weeks founded the Trinity College Historical Society which gave further impetus to strengthening the Department of History and supported a gradual shift from local to world history topics. By 1923, when Trinity College was ready to transition into Duke University, six semester hours of history course work was required for graduation. William K. Boyd and William T. Laprade formed the foundation of the History Department at Duke University, with Boyd's focus in American History with a concentration on Southern history and Laprade's focus on British history. In 1923, E. Malcolm Carroll joined the history faculty and shifted his research from American to continental European history to suit a void in research focus within the department. Between 1925 and 1939 the Department of History grew from six members to eighteen.
The transition from Trinity College to Duke University also included not only a change in name but also a shift from a small liberal arts college to a research university and consequently the emphasis of the Department of History. Under the direction of Boyd and President William Preston Few, the University sought to expand its collection of books and primary source material in the library to facilitate a new faculty concentration on original research and substantive contributions to historical understanding through scholarly publication. By the end of the 1930s, the Department of History had added five new faculty members that would spend their entire careers at Duke University: historian of British and Commonwealth history, William B. Hamilton; military historian Theodore Ropp; Harold T. Parker, historian of Revolutionary and Napoleonic France; English Rennaisance specialist Arthur B. Ferguson; and Richard L. Watson, Jr., historian of the Progressive Era and early twentieth-century United States.
Other noteworthy faculty joined Duke in the decades following the Second World War including Emeriti Professors Joel Colton in European history in 1947, Anne F. Scott in Women's History, military historian I.B. Holley, Peter H. Wood and Robert F. Durden, historian of the 19th century U.S. South, the Duke family, and author of The Launching of Duke University: 1925-1949 published by Duke University Press.
Currently the Department of History operates with a Chair and Directors of Graduate and Undergraduate Studies. The chairman is appointed by the Provost on the basis of the department's recommendations and in consultation with the Dean of Arts and Sciences and the Dean of the Graduate School. The chairman is appointed to a three-year term and will normally serve no more than two consecutive terms. The chairman is the principal point of contact between the department and central administration and is responsible for proposing appointees for the director of graduate and undergraduate studies; departmental committees; arrangement of the schedule of courses and teaching assignments; budget preparation, proposals, and departmental spending. Also, the chairman is to insure excellence in the faculty and to take the initiative in determining departmental needs and faculty prospects. However, the chair must cultivate the active cooperation and consent of his colleagues in order to maintain the collegial integrity of the department.
Portions of this Historical Note were adopted from Robert F. Durden, The Launching of Duke University: 1924-1949 (Duke University Press, 1993), 131-138.
Collection Overview
The records of the Department of History contain material pertaining to the operation and activity of the Department and various faculty members. The material ranges in date from 1932-2002, bulk 1951-1985. The records are divided into seven series: course papers, subject files, administrative files, inactive faculty files, Nixon Library files, external review, and Oral History Transcripts.
The Course Papers series is composed of I.B. Holley's History 195/196, "The Concept of a University," miscellaneous, and Richard Watson course papers. I.B. Holley's History 195/196 course papers deal with topics relevant to the history and development of Trinity College and Duke University. A majority of the Watson course papers consist of oral history projects in which students interviewed family members about their personal experiences during the Great Depression, the New Deal, and the Second World War. Course papers range in date from 1954-2003, bulk 1966-1992. Subject files contain a sampling of various departmental material including directories, handbooks, minutes and memoranda, and newsletters.
Administrative files (1932-1985) include material pertaining to the activities of the Office of the Chair and Directors of Graduate and Undergraduate Studies. Material present in Office of the Chair includes correspondence and memoranda. Also present are minutes and notes from various committees including Committee on Courses and Curriculum. Among the Chairs included are William T. Laprade (1937-1952), Charles Sydnor (1952-1954), E. Malcolm Carroll (1954-1957), John R. Alden (1957-1960), Richard Watson (1960-1967), Joel Colton (1967-1970), and Anne F. Scott. Director of Graduate Studies includes correspondence, memoranda, communication with the Graduate School, and notes and minutes from various graduate committees. Among the Directors included in the series are William T. Laprade, Robert H. Woody, Robert F. Durden, Charles R. Young, and Anne F. Scott. Director of Undergraduate Studies consists of correspondence, memoranda, and material from various undergraduate committees. A majority of the material was accumulated during the long tenure of Frederic B.M. Hollyday; but also includes material accumulated by Joel Colton, Robert Durden, Theodore Ropp, and Stephen A. Young. Major subjects throughout include American Historical Association and Review, Southern Historical Association, Trinity College Historical Society, and the Humanities and Russian Cooperative with the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill.
Four small series conclude the collection: Inactive faculty, Nixon Library, external review files, and Oral History Techniques. Inactive faculty files consist of alphabetically arranged name files of faculty: full professors, assistant and associate professors, and visiting instructors. Files for long-term faculty include obituaries and funeral programs. Nixon Library files contain correspondence, memoranda, and clippings from various periodicals, both local and national, pertaining to faculty reaction to the proposed location of the Nixon Library and Archives on the campus of Duke University. External Review files contain material accumulated by Professor John Cell during an external departmental review in 1999/2000 and include reports prepared by various departmental officers for the review team, a copy of the final report and responses, and files from a 1994 Departmental review. The final series contains papers and transcripts of oral history interviews held by students of History 279: Oral History Techniques with faculty, staff, and students concerning contemporary race relations at Duke University.
Related Material
E. Malcolm Carroll Papers, circa 1930-1954
Duke University Archives/David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Center for Canadian Studies Records, 1971-1993
Duke University Archives/David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Joel G. Colton Papers, 1942-1983
Duke University Archives/David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Robert F. Durden Reference Collection, circa 1965-2001
Duke University Archives/David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
William Baskerville Hamilton Papers, circa 1700-1972
Duke University Archives/David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Frederic B.M. Hollyday Papers, 1943-1971
Duke University Archives/David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
William Thomas Laprade Papers, 1660-1975, bulk 1898-1975
Duke University Archives/David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Oral History Program Collection, 1973-1978, 1992, undated
Duke University Archives/David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Anne Firor Scott Papers, 1963-2002
Duke University Archives/David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Trinity College Historical Society Collection, [1492?]-1981
Duke University Archives/David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Richard L. Watson, Jr. Papers, 1941-1989
Duke University Archives/David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Robert H. Woody Papers, 1927-1985
Duke University Archives/David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Historiography -- United States; Duke University -- History -- 20th century; Colton, Joel, 1918-2011; Duke University. Department of History; Duke University. Committee Against the Nixon-Duke Library; American Historical Association; Duke University. Department of History; Hamilton, William Baskerville, 1908-1972; Laprade, William Thomas, 1883-1975; Hollyday, Frederic B. M.; Duke University. Department of History -- Faculty; Holley, I.B. (Irving Brinton), 1919-; Duke University. Nixon Library Committee; Durden, Robert Franklin; Watson, Richard L.; Woody, Robert H. (Robert Hilliard), 1903-; Scott, Anne Firor, 1921-; Southern Historical Association; Trinity College (Durham, N.C.) -- History; Trinity College Historical Society
- Course Papers, 1954-2003, bulk 1966-1992, 7 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains student papers from various history courses offered at Duke. Professor I.B. Holley's History 195/196, "The Concept of a University," papers deal with topics relevant to the history and development of Trinity College and Duke University. Miscellaneous course papers include a bound volume from Prof. Laura F. Edwards "Women Making History in the Nineteenth-Century South," along with teacher evaluations from Prof. I.B. Holley's History 312. In addition to general topics in twentieth century American history, a majority of the Watson course papers consist of oral history projects in which students interviewed family members about their personal experiences during the Great Depression, the New Deal, and the Second World War.
  - I.B. Holley, History 195/196, "The Concept of a University," 1974-1991
    Papers composed for Professor I.B. Holley's History 195/196, "The Concept of a University," which deal with topics related to the history and development of Trinity College and Duke University.
    - Allums, Chris. "Duke Forest: 60 Years as a Laboratory for University Research and Teaching." (1991) (Box 1)
    - Amen, Barbara. "The Development of a Coordinate College for Women at Trinity College, N.C., 1904-1924: A Struggle for Equality." (1974) (Box 1)
    - Bain, Bruce. "The Changing Status of Political Science at Trinity College and Duke University, 1849-1941: The Evolution of a Department." (1978) (Box 1)
    - Bartolome, Jorge L. "The Rocky Path of Business Education at Duke: How OutsideDevelopments Forced a University to Take Action." (1991) (Box 1)
    - Becker, Michael J. "One Nuclear Bomb Can Ruin Your Whole Day: Civil Defense at Duke University." (1991) (Box 1)
    - Biro, Peter. "Bypassed by a Revolution: Development of Engineering Education at Duke University, 1887-1966." (1991) (Box 1)
    - Booher, Bridget. "Death of a Romantic Revolutionary: Sheldon Robert Harte, Duke 1937." (1991) (Box 1)
    - Boone, Joseph Allen. "A New Perspective on the Role of Academic Freedom in the 1903 Bassett Affair at Trinity College." (1974) (Box 1)
    - Brotherson, James R. "The Early Development of the Student News Media at Trinity College and Duke University, 1847-1927." (1974) (Box 1)
    - Cantlay, Donna. "The Growth of Modern Languages at Trinity and Duke, 1850-1940."(1980) (Box 1)
    - Carbonara, Mary Jean. "The Evolution of the Sarah P. Duke Gardens at Duke University: The Growth of an Aesthetic Institution." (1978) (Box 1)
    - Carter, Glenn J. "The Rise to National Stature of the Duke University Law School, 1927-1935." (1978) (Box 1)
    - Casey, Ted. "The Future of the Primates." (1991) (Box 1)
    - Cassedy, Jane C. "Towers and Spires: The Construction of the Collegiate Gothic Duke University Campus, 1927-1930." (1978) (Box 1)
    - Cederberg, James A. "Eruditio et Religio: The Manifest Destiny of Duke University."(1974) (Box 1)
    - Conrad, Frederick L., Jr. "The Development of an Institutionalized Fraternity System Trinity College: 1870-1920." (1980) (Box 2)
    - Cortegiano, Mark. "When Legal Theory Meets Economics: A History of Alternative Dispute Resolution and the Private Adjudication Center, Inc." (1991) (Box 2)
    - Cox, Stephanie H. "Why Should the Singing Tower Sing at Duke University?." (1978) (Box 2)
    - Curtin, Helen B. "Undergraduate Religious Instruction at Trinity College and Duke University, 1896-1941: Denominational Training or Non-Denominational Education?" (1978) (Box 2)
    - D'Esposito, Jim. "The History Department at Trinity College, 1887-1924: Evolving Concepts of a Liberal Education." (1976) (Box 2)
    - Davis, Alvah B. "From Display Case to Museum: The Use of Art and Artifacts in Teaching at Duke University, 1925-1975." (1976) (Box 2)
    - Ferguson, Kate. "Integrating the Arts and Academia: The First Ten Years of the Institute of the Arts." (1991) (Box 2)
    - Fields, Peggy. "Hail to Thee, Dear Alma Mater: The Institutionalization of the Alumni Association at Trinity College." (1978) (Box 2)
    - Flores, Leticia Y. "Testing the University Waters: Freewater, an Experiment in Student Freedom and Responsibility." (1991) (Box 2)
    - Ford, John B. "Agent of Change: John F. Crowell and Curricular Reform at Trinity College, 1887-1894." (1978) (Box 2)
    - Forrester, William W. "The Impact of the Depression on Duke University: Progress in Hard Times." (1974) (Box 2)
    - Frinkle, Robert B. "Conduct and Character: Developmental Education and Social Regulations for Male Undergraduates at Trinity College and Duke University, 1891-1934." (1974) (Box 2)
    - Fuller, Elizabeth L. "The Legal Aid Clinic and the Duke University Law School." (1980) (Box 2)
    - Futrell, Ashley B., Jr. "From Cap Gun to H-bomb: Continuing Justifications for Basketball within the Academic Community of Trinity College and Duke University, 1906-1942." (1978) (Box 2)
    - Gallagher, Carole L. "A History of the Relationship Between Duke University and the Methodist Church, 1924-1975." (1976) (Box 2)
    - Garvin, Gregory. "The Duke Computer Laboratory: The Foundation Had Been Shaped for Future Development." (1974) (Box 2)
    - Hamilton, Curtis. "Bus Transportation at Duke: A University- Owned System." (1991) (Box 3)
    - Hamilton, Kayla M. "The Duke University Talent Identification Program: Respected Honor or Playboy Program?." (1991) (Box 3)
    - Hanberry, Jane Morley. "The Duke Vigil: A Culmination of Issues, 1966-1968." (1976) (Box 3)
    - Harrison, Brenda. "Public Reaction to the Duke Endowment from 1924-1972." (1974) (Box 3)
    - Hepburn, Matthew J. "The Development of the Vitrectomy: Engineering and Medicine Combine to Overcome Blindness." (1991) (Box 3)
    - Hohman, Timothy S. "Aspirations and Transformations: A Study of the Roman Catholic Church at Duke University." (1991) (Box 3)
    - Houk, Mary Bentley. "Design of a Duchess: The Education of Duke Women, 1930-1964." (1991) (Box 3)
    - Jackson, Tim. "A History of the Honor Society of 9019, Trinity College and Duke University, 1890-1943: A Most Honorable Organization." (1980) (Box 3)
    - Kassebaum, Douglas W. "The Sources and Inception of Long-Range Planning at Duke University, 1955-1961: A Vision of Things to Come." (1991) (Box 3)
    - Lamb, L. William. "William Kenneth Boyd, William Washington Flowers, and the Development of the George Washington Flowers Memorial Collection." (1991) (Box 3)
    - Lessley, Bryan. "Corpore Sano at Duke: Physical Activity Programs in a Liberal Education." (1980) (Box 3)
    - Malechek, David. "Attitudes Toward Football at Trinity College and Duke University: A Study in Shifting Values, 1887-1943." (1976) (Box 3)
    - Maupin, David. "Public Safety at Duke." (1991) (Box 3)
    - Milford, Timothy A. "Nurture of a Lesser God: Religion at Duke University, 1924-1990." (1991) (Box 3)
    - Pearl, David. "Duke University and the NROTC (1941-1972): Amity, Enmity, and Compromise." (1974) (Box 3)
    - Perretti, Peter. "The Divinity School and Desegregation: An Abortive Blow Against the Status Quo, 1948-1952." (1976) (Box 3)
    - Ross, John. "Trying to Catch Up: The Evolution of Philanthropy in America and Duke University." (1991) (Box 4)
    - Rudman, Michael. "The Occupational Safety and Health Act of 1971 and the Consequent Development of the Safety Program at Duke University." (1978) (Box 4)
    - Russo, Frank T. "The Fraternity System at Trinity College and Duke University: Its Relation to the Administration, 1871-1941." (1976) (Box 4)
    - Sauls, Timothy. "The Eno River Reservoir Controversy, 1966-1973: A Case Study in the Power of Public Opposition." (1978) (Box 4)
    - Semans, William M. "The Code of the Moment." (1991) (Box 4)
    - Smith, Laura. "A History of Child Care at Duke: The Development of New and Innovative Services for the youngest of the University Community." (1991) (Box 4)
    - Smoot, W. Scott. "Dramatic Changes: A History of the Duke Players and Its Relation to the Academic Curriculum of Duke University." (1980) (Box 4)
    - Snyder, Bruce. "Wallace, Football at Duke, and Goals of Higher Education." (1974) (Box 4)
    - Stevens, Jeanne. "Climbing Like Kudzu: A Study of Research and Professionalism at Duke University Through World War II." (1991) (Box 4)
    - Summerell, Fran. "Trinity Park School, 1898-1922: A Methodist Remedy in Central North Carolina." (1976) (Box 4)
    - Tenney, Bryan E. "A History of Duke Baseball, 1889-1980." (1980) (Box 4)
    - Wang, Theodore G. "Stagnation and Rejuvenation: The Decline and Rise of the Study of Classics at Duke University, 1930-1990." (1991) (Box 4)
    - Weinstein, Andrew. "Bourbon and Bookworms: Ten Years of Turbulence within the Duke Alcohol Policy." (1991) (Box 4)
    - Widera, Bernard J. "Forty Years of Liberal Education in Practice: Phi Kappa Psi at Duke, 1934-1974." (1980) (Box 4)
    - Wille, Brian. "Theodore W. Minah: High Standards Without High Expense." (1991) (Box 4)
    - Wolff, Stephen I. "The Early History of the Research Council at Trinity College and Duke University, 1919-1941: A Vital Link in the Launching of the University." (1978) (Box 4)
    - Worthington, Tom. "William McDougall and the Beginnings of Psychology at Duke University, 1926-1929." (1974) (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous course papers, 1956-2003
    - Ballance, Frank. "The Associated Farmers of California, 1934-1939." [1961?] (Box 5)
    - Cooper, Bridget. "The Spark of Democracy: Adolfo Suarez and the Union of the Democratic Center." (Senior Honors, Dr. TePaske, 1995) (Box 5)
    - Harkins, Matthew J. "Struggling with Sexism: An Examination of Men Acting for Change." (Oral History, Dr. Goodwyn, 1994) (Box 5)
    - Hickey, Carl. R. "Charles Abram Ellwood: A Study of Gradual Disillusionment, Part I: A Man of Hope and Confidence." (271, Dr. Parker, 1959) (Box 5)
    - Hickey, Carl R. "Charles A. Elwood: A Social Gospel Figure Within Sociology." (271-272, Dr. Parker; 249-150, Dr. Holley, 1960) (Box 5)
    - Lauer, Ellen R. "Erudito et Religio, 'Progress,' and Academic Freedom." (Draft, 1956) (Box 5)
    - McNally, John. "The Rise of Engineering at Trinity College: 1838-1924." (249-250, Dr. Holley, 1966) (Box 5)
    - Moorhead, Joanna. "The 1966 Cooley-Gardner Election." (195D, 1971) (Box 5)
    - Stewart, Jr., Carl J. "The Shaping of American Neutrality, 1935-1937." (Honors Thesis, 202, Drs. Parker and Holley, [1958?]) (Box 5)
    - Wilson, Robin. "The History of Alcohol at Duke University Since 1960." (101N, Dr. James Roberts, 1990) (Box 5)
    - "Women Outside the Box in the Nineteenth-Century U.S. South," bound essays, (195s, Women Making History in the Nineteenth-Century U.S. South, Dr. Laura F. Edwards, 2003) (Box 5)
    - Holley 312, Teacher Evaluations (3 Folders), 1966 fall-1969 fall (Box 5)
    - Holley 312, Teacher Evaluations (5 Folders), 1971 fall-1974 spring, undated (Box 5)
  - Richard Watson course papers, 1954-1995
    Papers from various courses offered by Professor Watson dealing primarily with topics in early twentieth-century American history.
    - A.M. Thesis (Box 6)
      - Davis, Marie. "The Briand-Kellogg pact, 1928-1929: Forces Leading to the Ratification of the Treaty for the Renunciation of War." (1954) (Box 6)
    - History 93S
      - Coleman, Rachel. "The Greenbaums and the Etras: New York City Jews and the Great Depression." (1993) (Box 6)
      - Ellis, Atiba. "The Occupation of the Allen Building at Duke University: The Synthesis of Student Revolts." (1992) (Box 6)
      - Frichione, Cheryl. "Chicken Farms and Railroad Apartments: A Story of Surviving the Great Depression." (1993) (Box 6)
      - Hollar, Dave. "My Grandmother in the Depression." (1993) (Box 6)
      - Procaro, Lauren. "The Great Depression: One Family's Experience." (1992) (Box 6)
      - Spooner, Marc. "A Family History during the Great Depression." (1992) (Box 6)
      - Taylor, Charlotte. "Skeletons from the Closet: Uncle Dick the Embezzler." (1992) (Box 6)
      - [unknown]. "My Family History during the Great Depression." [1992?] (Box 6)
    - History 113
      - Nye, Charles Howard. "The Bassett Affair and the Press." (1983) (Box 6)
    - History 114
      - Allen, Frank. "The Allen-Bowles Family History: The Depression Years." (1979) (Box 6)
      - Atkinson, Mike. "Princeton, North Carolina and the Great Depression." [1982?] (Box 6)